so
[Music]
it's already six in the morning
um
[Music]
today is my birthday you know i'm 13.
to
wow
[Music]
ah mr frank
i almost forgot
would you please give this to anne it's
a little present for her birthday i do
hope she likes it and this is for me
otto
thank you co-poist thank you me i'll
give them to her at home as i told you
we will soon be going into hiding would
you be willing to assume the risk of
looking after us and being our outside
contact yes we'll be needing you very
soon
[Music]
hello i'm home
daddy
daddy it's you oh you brought home lots
of surprises i'm sure let me see them
let me see them
a little patience anne i'll give you
meep and corporals gifts in the meantime
oh yes please
take my case yes daddy thank you
let's go inside noah
hello
daddy you're back at last thank heaven
you're home safe
how are you edith did you have a
pleasant day dear
can i open my presents now please daddy
can i please
happy birthday dear stan here these are
for you
thank you
[Music]
the one with the pretty ribbon on it is
from meep
and open your presents carefully
if not you'll spoil this lovely paper
and the ribbon everything is so very
precious during wartime yes i know
a book on the cinema
oh
that's greta garbo and
and fred astaire oh i really adore them
and my dear you should look at the
package underneath it
hmm
oh it's a dream come true
a diary
[Music]
what a wonderful idea thank you daddy
it's from your mother as well we both
had the same idea don't you think you
should thank her too
oh i'm sorry thank you mommy
take advantage of your carefree life
while there's still time
otto i'm frightened we were forced to
leave germany because of hitler and now
they're making us wear yellow stars on
our clothing in holland
yes i know the only way to escape the
nazis now is to hide from them to
disappear
what will become of us this horrible war
has me so worried for anne and margo
edith listen
you know as well as i do that it's too
late and too dangerous for us to try to
get out of amsterdam kopoys has brought
supplies and furniture to our hideout in
addition meep is going to help us so be
brave
friday june 12 1942
you are the nicest present of all
i hope i shall be able to confide in you
completely as i never have been able to
do in anyone before
and i hope that you will be a great
support and comfort to me
i want you to be the true friend for
whom i've waited so long
and i'm going to call you kitty
because of the anti-jewish degrees daddy
can't take the tram like everyone else
and has to go to his office at the other
end of the city on foot
ever since the german invasion in 1940
amsterdam has been occupied by the army
and now we jews must wear a yellow star
in our clothing if not we can be
arrested
[Music]
my sister margo and i have been
transferred to the jewish secondary
school
anyway i'm so glad to be in the same
class with liz
and you know everyone is saying you're
in love with harry goldblum we've walked
to school together once or twice but
that's all anyway that's not what he
says
three a minus six a b plus five b
plus three a since you seem to be so
well informed tell me what else he's
saying about me
guess that i'm much too young for him no
he says he prefers you to fanny that she
puts him to sleep
give me that
you're jealous just because harry and i
are friends
it doesn't mean the whole world
joking he's 16 and he thinks all your
friends are children but he likes you
because you're his alarm clock what
is that
my word miss frank
why this sudden enthusiasm for algebra
that's enough now quiet down who would
like to solve a problem at the
blackboard
no volunteers
why don't we have
[Music]
soon and no more algebra
oh how i'd love to go to the cinema
again
but even that is forbidden to jews
just as it's forbidden to ride the trams
to use a car to go out after eight at
night jews must hand in their bicycles
too
being without a bicycle is one of the
most awful things to bear if you live in
holland
you know it's a shame we went assigned
to grab the beach in this heat
that was a close call i'll never take my
bicycle out again
liz always says i'm afraid to do
anything cause it may be forbidden
[Music]
hmm
just a second i'm coming
yes it's a labor camp call-up notice for
margot frank
is it for me
[Music]
dear kitty our friends mr cooper smith
and her husband came to our house that
same night to discuss what we should do
margot who's only 16 has received a
call-up notice to go to a labor camp in
germany
she's very frightened because everyone
knows what that means
should we let her be doomed to this
of course we won't let her go
daddy has decided that all four of us
will go into hiding tomorrow morning
and not wait until they come to get us
i'm so frightened we're here to help you
mrs franklin edith please we all need to
show courage this is the call of notice
beginning tomorrow we're going to have
to hide
corpus will you still help of course
otto
[Music]
there my bag is full
are you ready to go edith
oh i'm terrified for the children and
for ourselves too
i'm afraid of being stopped in the
street we're giving up everything we
have
edith follow the itinerary i gave you
and don't forget to act as naturally as
possible if you do everything will be
just fine i assure you you go with margo
and we'll meet you at the hiding place
just as we planned
[Music]
5 30 in the morning we're taking as much
as we possibly can
no jew in our situation would dream of
going out with a suitcase full of
clothing
[Music]
i'm not going to be able to walk
normally with all these clothes on you'd
be warm at the north pole
it's time to go girls are you ready oh
and don't forget to give the cat some
milk before we go
uh but daddy i was hoping i could take
moksha with me to the hiding place
oh please daddy
noah
i'm sorry but it's impossible it would
be far too dangerous
we're already wearing yellow stars we'd
attract even more attention if we took
him
i've left a note for the neighbors
saying goodbye and asking them to look
after him so don't worry come now
say goodbye to him i understand i'm sad
too but we have no choice
you'll see i promise to come back for
you very soon
come in
[Music]
we really must go now get your things
there's no time to lose leave mulcher
there you'll come with me and margo
you'll go with your mother
now we've a long walk so let's hurry up
but daddy where are we going
i think it's better that i don't tell
you
here margo
take this
i feel as if i'm in an adventure film
[Music]
hmm
and we've got to go now
[Music]
hmm
and
this way
[Music]
where are we going daddy is it still far
to away
[Music]
hmm
walk normally and just ignore him
[Music]
ah
hmm
[Music]
can i go up daddy yes go on
come up man
daddy go ahead
[Music]
come with me
give me your things
[Music]
here we are i don't believe it
huh
go on it's all right
[Music]
come in margo and mrs frank are already
here
don't be afraid dear go on
daddy
so this is the mysterious hiding place
that's right anne this is it
when margo's call-up notice came we
realized we would have to go into hiding
immediately that's why things aren't
quite set up but why didn't anyone tell
me our hiding place is right upstairs
from your office we had to make sure
that very few people knew about it and
we thought it too big a secret for a
little girl i'm not a little girl
anymore and i know how to keep a secret
this will be your room
[Music]
the dining room
it's so steep the pantry
what's in here
you can open it
[Music]
now listen to me everyone for as long as
we're here the most important rule is
not to make a sound during office hours
not to walk around no one must know that
the frank family is hiding in this house
obviously we won't be able to open the
windows
we'll have to cover them so that the
neighbors can't see us day or night
and you'll help me make some thick
curtains unpack the cartons put things
in the cupboards and set up the beds and
the bedding
margo you organize the kitchen yes daddy
edith you should rest you look very
tired
does everyone understand let's begin
mrs frank i'll be doing the shopping
every day and i'll bring everything up
just after midday as soon as the
employees leave for lunch oh i don't
know how to thank you i don't know what
we do without you meep
it's eight o'clock i'd better go down to
the office i'll leave you now the
employees will be here any minute
don't make any noise for the time being
wait until noon or tonight to unpack all
of your cartons we're all deeply
grateful to you meep let's hope that
this horrible wall will be over soon and
that we can leave here
goodbye for now
everything will be fine mommy you'll see
uh
ah
what's wrong
i have to use the toilet
ugh
you won't believe me kitty but there are
even special hours for using the toilet
what was that
don't forget not a sound
hello everyone
hello well done
we can't hear a thing from downstairs
nothing
you do realize colpoyce it's not easy to
sit still for so many hours at a time oh
i think it's all right for you to talk
as long as you remember to keep your
voices down
it would certainly make the time go by
faster wouldn't it anne
well i hope you understood what meep
just said anne you should use your
sister as an example
well i think it's about time we made
this place a little more livable
and
is everything all right
[Music]
you're hanging up pictures of your
favorite movie stars and a picture of
our queen wilhelmina too yes everybody
laughs at me because i'm so keen on the
royal family but i don't care i just
hope that this war is over very soon and
that our beloved queen and her entire
family come back from their exile in
london safe and sound
awardo how long do you think we'll have
to stay here
[Music]
margo can you hear the church bells
i'm trying to sleep margo
i love them especially at night because
you can count on them
what a beautiful sky
be careful that no one sees you
daddy said the van dan family will be
coming into hiding with us
i hear that their son peter is very nice
nice looking too
i'll never be able to sleep with those
church bells ringing every 15 minutes
look at the stars margo
[Music]
dear kitty i can't tell you how
oppressive it is never to be able to go
outdoors
also i'm very afraid we'll be discovered
and shot that is not exactly a pleasant
prospect
we have to whisper and tread lightly
during the day
otherwise the people in the warehouse
which is just below might hear us
[Music]
we're almost there
welcome to our home in hiding hello mrs
frank hello
otto
hello thank you so much for taking us in
you know my wife edith of course this is
our eldest daughter margot and ann who's
now 13 years old and i would like you to
meet petronella my wife
and this is peter our only son
and you'll never guess who's inside here
his cat mushi he wouldn't leave him
behind and he has become part of the
family
but
you mean you brought a cat with you
didn't anyone tell you that that we
don't want anything it won't be a burden
to you at all peter will take care of
him the problem is he has to be fed he's
gonna dirty things and he could give us
all away
i know how you feel anne but mushi will
become your friend too perhaps but for
now why don't you welcome the vandans
hello
peter the van danson is just 16
a kind of soft shy gawky boy can't
expect much from his company
mr van dan what's been happening outside
since we left and do you know what's
become of my best friend release gossler
what did you say you heard me and i
really would like an answer mr van dan
you know there are thousands of call-up
notices raids and arrests on the outside
it's a mad house i'm sorry but i don't
know a thing about your little friend
lise
why should we worry about others we have
enough problems of our own
yes you're right
oh what a nice large pile of clean
sheets you've got i would suggest that
we use these first what do you think
hmm
i thought it would be much better if
each family used its own sheets i agree
with mummy it would make more sense is
that how little girls are supposed to
talk to grown-ups is that the way you
were taught to behave first of all i'm
not a little girl mrs van dan and
secondly don't forget you're in our home
well you ought to have been in our home
we were properly brought up it's absurd
that anne is so frightfully spoiled i
wouldn't put up with it if anne were my
daughter
hmm thank heavens i'm not
[Music]
let me see we do use my lovely table
service every day do you think that
makes more sense
you really don't know people until after
you've had a fight with them
anyway at least she's a good cook
hello girls your mother and i wanted to
talk to you for a minute
i can understand how you feel about the
vandans but if each of us doesn't give
just a little our lives in this house
are going to become unbearable you
should be grateful that we're together
in a safe place the situation is
difficult enough there's no sense in
making things harder but when she
insults me i can't just say nothing at
all try to ignore what she says
i have no problem at all with the
vandans
try to be more like your sister she
doesn't look for trouble she avoids it
respect your elders
and dear please i want you to show some
self-control that's all
[Music]
i think of our hiding as a dangerous
adventure romantic and interesting at
the same time
i can't grumble all day long
i've been given a lot a happy nature
cheerfulness and strength
every day i feel that i'm developing
inwardly
i see how beautiful nature is
why then should i be in despair
there you are you're always so kind and
helpful go on take it
thank you
oh you needn't thank me it's only
natural i'll deliver the potatoes to
your office later as usual
thank you i have fewer and fewer ration
tickets and things are more and more
expensive what's important is to keep
your spirits up and never lose heart
right
one of these days this damn wall will
end let's hope so
bye goodbye
goodbye
[Music]
so
hello meep
hello everyone how are you oh
help me please oh it's heavy
i found almost everything you asked me
for
but it wasn't easy
i have a few surprises for you as well
this is me oh thank you me tobacco thank
you so much what else
ah
and here's your movie magazine with all
your favorite films thank you
i thought you might like this autumn
leaf as a present
let me wait oh no
now look what you've done
i'm sorry anne
now for the big surprise huh
take it mr frank go on
i wonder what it is
oh
it's a
it's a book
perhaps you should open it
[Music]
oh meep it's a little radio how
wonderful now we can listen to the bbc
and radio orange for news of the free
world instead of nazi propaganda
newspapers
[Music]
it's forbidden to have a radio
so on top of clandestine jews
clandestine money for clandestine buying
on the black market weaken at a
clandestine radio
as the news from the outside gets worse
the radio helps to keep up our morale
this morning english and american troops
landed in tunis algiers casablanca and
iran ah this is not the end
i told you we had to remain optimistic
of the end
but it is perhaps the end of the
beginning i've just heard the voice of
winston churchill announcing to the free
world a decisive step towards the
liberation of europe
[Music]
algiers is here the allies are now in
control of north africa the next step
strategically should be in the
mediterranean region an invasion of
italy perhaps that's all well and good
but italy's far from here yes she's
right
not a day goes by without listening to
the voice of the free world from london
which keeps our spirits up in the hope
of being liberated very soon
the other good news is that meep is
going to spend the night here
you can't imagine how happy i am that
you're spending the night in the secret
annex with us i am too ann
look
[Music]
i saved the ribbon from my birthday
present wrapping
everyone laughed at me they said i was
doing up my hair to look like a movie
star
[Music]
i have lots of other colors too so i can
change whenever i feel like it i'm glad
you care about your appearance even in
hiding it's a very good thing
i would love to enjoy myself again ride
my bicycle breathe in real fresh air
i want to dance and travel and see the
whole world i know and i'm sure this
horrible war will be over soon
[Music]
wait let me do that
your hair is so soft do you brush it
often
[Music]
there
please i really want to know have my
friends and their families gone into
hiding too
i don't know and it's too dangerous to
ask around
what's happening outside well
the nazis round up jews both day and
night they're arrested in their houses
and on the street as well
they have to leave everything behind
their possessions are confiscated if
they refuse they're beaten or even
killed immediately they have no choice
at all
you're all safe here in the secret annex
as you call it but you've got to be very
careful
me
i love you so much
i'm afraid they'll arrest you because of
us
me
i'm scared
[Music]
mr frank you saved my life thank you the
danger is the same for aides for seven
consider this your home you know my wife
dear kitty great news we're taking in an
eighth person mr dussel a dentist
i'm not so crazy about sharing my room
with a stranger but you gotta be
prepared to make sacrifices for a good
cause anyway they didn't give me a
choice
every morning he does what he calls
exercise
[Music]
and guess where he prefers spending his
time in the water closet three four five
times a day 15 minutes each time while
the whole annex waits begging hey it's
my turn do you think he cares
not a bit
[Applause]
[Music]
what a cat
but i
i'm allergic to cats get that animal
away from me quickly
peter i think you had better take mushi
upstairs right away i'm asking you to
get rid of that cat immediately throw
him out you're here i don't want to see
him again is that clear do you
understand peter you heard what are you
waiting for go and get rid of mushy i
said he's making mr dussel ill go on go
on now get that cat out of here no peter
stay here don't listen to him mr dussel
i would like to tell you something once
and for all you've only just arrived
here and you've imposed your schedule on
all of us as well as your ridiculously
annoying habits mushi's not only a good
pet but he eats mice which is a big help
oh they're a pretentious little 13 year
old girl trying to teach me a lesson
that's enough i can't bear another
minute of this and i mr dussel i cannot
bear using the desk where i do my
writing under the pretext of needing it
to work on your silly so-called thesis
get out of my sight right now ouch and
not another word
this time you've gone too far apologize
immediately to dr dussell
and don't let it happen again
dr dussell please forgive me
i got carried away
hmm
you were really frightened weren't you
my little scaredy cat
uh
look who's here mushi it's anne she was
brave enough to stand up to mr duso you
should thank her let her give you a
cuddle
peter would it be all right with you if
i stayed here for a while in your room
why sure come in thanks for what you did
just now i'd have never dared
oh it was nothing just because they're
adults they think they can do anything
they want
you know ad i really admire you you do
yes you know what you want and you're
not a coward
oh well
who would ever be afraid of a nasty
doctor your cat was scared wasn't she
she
you're joking mooshi's a he not a she
would like to hold him a he who's
expecting kittens look can't you see how
round her tummy is give him to me huh
you're gonna see for yourself what he is
oh no mushy
come back
come back right now you're here
[Music]
you'll never get him out from under
there not going to hurt you come on
there i got him
now i'm going to show you
there he's a male you see
thank you
but i have seen quite enough she is a
male cat all right peter you win
thanks for the lesson leave me alone now
[Music]
ah
what's going on
i'm scared
and i'm here now
[Music]
calm down
how can anyone ever get used to any
aircraft noise
[Music]
oh daddy
i'm sorry
i'm frightened oh protect me
daddy please
sleep now
yes i'm not afraid
no i'm not afraid
[Music]
she's asleep now put her down
sleep well
sleep well my little aunt
dear kitty tonight is the first night of
hanukkah the festival of light of hope
we couldn't bring our menorah with us
so we made one of our own
[Music]
oh but
what are you doing mr frank you're
supposed to let it burn yes you're right
but given the present circumstances i
think we had better economize and
candles they may come in very handy one
day
may we all be blessed with good health
until the end of this terrible war and
our rapid liberation oh man
and no and stop acting silly take your
blanket off your head
you've had the flu for almost a week now
come on now sit up oh
dr ducel wants to examine your oh take
the blanket off your face no no
and please stop acting like a baby
no he i don't want him to touch me he's
a dentist not a real doctor i studied
medicine young lady whether you like it
or not
we don't want the flu to turn into
pneumonia
leave this to me
ah mommy help no time to stop mom you
won't help mr dussel's half death i'll
have you know i hear everything i need
to hear perfectly well
she'll be all right
it's been seven months since we went
into hiding in the secret annex
terrifying things are happening outside
resistance members are executed on the
street
machine gun fires a hundred times more
frightening than bombs
jewish families are arrested day and
night and deported no one is able to
keep out of it the whole world is at war
there is nothing we can do but wait
until the misery comes to an end
and
meeps here come
peace in 1943 that's what we all wish
and it's my favorite cake too
could i have that big piece just over
there and i'd like that one please
gentlemen let's not forget our manners
[Music]
thank you so much meep
let's hope that our wish for peace will
come true this year
i don't want to alarm you but i think
you should know that it's getting harder
and harder to find food for everyone
that is
i try my luck in the more distant
neighborhoods but after waiting in line
for hours i find there's almost nothing
i can buy oh
you string beans some cabbage a handful
of rotten potatoes what what'll become
of us it'll be easy finding you
provisions everything's become so
expensive on the black market meep don't
forget the risk you take of course our
reserves of cans and dried vegetables
won't last forever but
we'll just have to tighten our belts
that's all
meep i have an idea why don't you see if
you can find someone who would like to
buy my suit i won't hear of it we need
the money dear so why not
besides what do i need a suit for here
anyway if we can manage to sell it then
meep can buy food for us
all right mr vandan i'll try to find
someone who will buy it at a good price
me i don't want to take advantage of
your kindness but if you could find some
tobacco for me i would really be deeply
grateful
oh yeah
what a husband
dear kitty at the moment i'm going
through a period of feeling depressed my
longing to talk to someone became so
intense that somehow or other i took it
into my head to choose peter
is the radio broken
i hope you're going to be able to repair
it quickly young man
the radio might not have broken if you
didn't trip the knobs all the time do
you think you can fix it peter yes if he
promises not to touch it again are you
insinuating that i do not know how to
use a radio correctly
leave me alone i can't concentrate i'm
going up to the attic to work on it yes
go on peter change of air will do you
some good
he'd better be careful that he doesn't
break it permanently
[Music]
ugh
can i help you with anything peter
yes you can hold mushy for me
thank you
[Music]
do you ever think about what you want to
do later on when we leave here after the
war
i'd like to go to the dutch indies and
live on a plantation where it's sunny
i'm going to study art history and live
in london and paris for a while
it was just a loose wire that's all
it'll work fine now
let's hope we hear only good news over
it
i'm longing so long for everything to
talk for freedom for friends to be alone
i can feel my heart beating as if it's
saying can't you satisfy my longings at
last
be careful not to be seen by anyone
outside i am careful i just want to
breathe some fresh air
you're right
i would gladly give up eating if i could
only breathe some fresh air when it's
spring too isn't it
[Music]
i feel the awakening of spring in me i
feel it in my body and in my soul
i think what is happening to me is so
wonderful and not only what can be seen
on my body but all that is taking place
inside
and would you like to talk a bit
you know margo i'm a woman now this is
just my third period but i feel that in
spite of the pain the unpleasantness and
the tiredness i have a wonderfully sweet
secret inside of me
oh look at the birds
i adore them i envy their freedom
would you let me read your diary one day
well yes perhaps certain parts of it i
have the feeling that you're jealous of
my seeing peter alone that it makes you
sad no you're wrong
it can't be much fun being a fifth wheel
i'm used to it don't say that
i'm happy for you that you found a
friend here
and what do you want to do in the future
hmm
my greatest wish is to become a
journalist and then later on a famous
writer
i can shake off everything when i write
everything
my sorrows disappeared my courage is
reborn you see yes
i would like to be a teacher or midwife
and take care of little babies after the
war what i want to do is to publish a
book that i'm going to call the secret
annex i only hope i'm capable of doing
it my diary will certainly be a big help
you'll do it and i'm absolutely sure of
it you're very ambitious and you have a
lot of talent
it's nice talking together like really
close friends
yes that's what two sisters should be
like
[Music]
dear kitty anti-aircraft fire bombing
monstrous air battles we've forgotten
what a quiet night is like the house
trembles
the bombs don't fall too far from here
imagine kitty the annex and flames and
all of us having to leave
it would be a last resort since being
out on the street would be just as
dangerous for us as the bombings
[Music]
mommy i only have one blouse my
sweater's too small it barely covers my
navel what are you doing i'm mending
margo's blouse for the tenth time can't
you see that i'm a woman now all of my
undergarments are too small and worn out
i can't wear them
you shouldn't complain think about the
horrors in the world people dying you
should consider yourself lucky to be
alive and safe
you really know how to raise someone's
morale mummy
i'm sorry but do you think my morale is
high with this interminable war you may
think you're a woman now but you're just
an insolent little child listen mummy
i'm not a child anymore the long months
shut up in here have matured me more
than you think
if you just let me be myself i might be
able to find some happiness here
it's shameful you spend so much time
alone with peter you shouldn't go up to
the attic so often to see him it makes
no sense at all to encourage him
oh
[Music]
peter
don't you find it surprising that anna's
so quiet this evening
mother why can't you leave her alone for
once
well her silence is rather surprising
she must be thinking about the next
chapter of her masterpiece or about the
incomparable taste of this rotten potato
yeah
will you all leave her alone
[Music]
if god lets me live i will achieve more
than mommy has
i will not remain insignificant
i'm going to work for mankind
you know kitty it's paradise here
compared to the outside
many of our jewish friends have been
arrested by the gestapo and then
transported in cattle cars we assume
that most of them are murdered the bbc
talks about concentration camps and
gassing
please my friend oh
no
no please please
please
[Music]
please take my hand
don't leave me
please
i'm here ladies
liz i'm here i'm here
calm down
it was a nightmare it's all right now
go back to sleep
don't worry go back to sleep
oh
here thank you
happy birthday my dear
[Music]
oh thank you it's so pretty
and a pair of shoes too
for your 14th birthday everybody in the
annex chipped in you're growing so
quickly you really need them
thank you
[Music]
oh it's that horrible catamaran
come on
[Music]
oh mushy
what a lovely young lady you look really
nice happy birthday
and not a child anymore
[Music]
[Applause]
thanks to you all
with your cigarettes and pipe tobacco
all our money is going off in smoke
get me away from her before i before i
do something
again and again i ask myself would it
not have been better for us if we hadn't
gone into hiding if we were all dead now
and not going through all this misery
[Music]
i want to go on living even after my
death and that's why i'm grateful for
this gift of being able to write and
express my innermost thoughts
for tomorrow's french lesson go over
your irregular verbs
[Music]
thank you margo
dearest kitty winter is really severe
and our food supply has gone further and
further down stale dried up bread
potatoes and salad that have a sweet
rotting smell dumplings made out of
flour that are so heavy and sticky that
you feel as if they're rocks in your
stomach when you're hungry though you
can't complain
we need money so i've decided that we're
going to sell your fur coat what you'll
do no such thing i love that coat and i
won't let you sell it under any
circumstances you understand will you
stop being so selfish you've had that
old rabbit fur for almost 20 years now
meep can probably sell it for 300
florins me selfish i don't believe what
i'm hearing if you spent less on your
horrible tobacco we would have money to
buy food and besides i have every
intention of wearing my coat when the
war is over when the war is over you
must be dreaming
we have to survive
and we can't survive if we have nothing
to eat
i can't take it anymore this water's so
long
the nazis are about to win in the end
bite your tongue
peter
[Music]
it's me peter
hello mushi
[Music]
you've been crying
my parents fight so often
if only i didn't have to be stuck with
them all of the time oh peter i know how
you feel and i'd love to help you if you
wanted me to it gnaws away at you even
if you don't say anything you still take
all their fighting to heart
[Music]
i'm so happy to be here together with
you
so maya
i
we're not
we're not alone anymore
[Music]
[Laughter]
this is the second time we've celebrated
new year's here meep we don't know how
to thank you for the risks you've taken
to help us these last 18 months
don't thank me and i'll continue to do
my best
until the liberation and let's hope
that's soon
yes the end of the war in 1944
that's right we must never give up hope
meep
would you try to sell my lovely fur coat
darling wait perhaps you shouldn't sell
it no no i behaved very foolishly the
last time we talked about it hear me try
to get 300.
[Music]
peace at last in 1944
yes
i love you
hmm
edith
what stay here shh
why what is
be careful
what could it be
a thief perhaps i'd better go down and
see
stay here
stop it
it must have been burglars and when they
heard the noise they got frightened and
ran if they suspect that there are jews
hiding here they could give us away it's
all because of that miserable cat how
many times have i said we have got to
get rid of him
i can't take anymore shh
somebody is opening the front door
hey we better check this
an open door at this time of night
that's very strange
[Music]
look at the mess in here
burglars must have gotten into this
office that's why the front door was
broken in
i must have made a fast getaway look at
this
yeah forget it it doesn't lead anywhere
it's just a bookcase
yeah you're right it's late let's go
back and find a report that night i
really thought the gestapo would find us
and that we would all be deported
yes
[Music]
mr frank i don't want to alarm everyone
but i think you should know that the man
who i buy vegetables from has just been
arrested he must suspect something about
us let's hope he doesn't say anything
under questioning now where am i going
to get food from be twice as careful
from now on maybe your life is at stake
as i'm sure you realize i'll explain the
problem to the others we'll just have to
make do with less than
[Music]
burying our heads in the sand has led
nowhere while nazi germany was rearming
for war no one in europe mounted a
finger to prevent it and now the entire
world is paying for it
ah it's time for the news ah this is
london this morning general eisenhower
announced the landing of allied troops
in normandy with these words
a landing was made this morning on the
coast of france by troops of the allied
expeditionary force
this landing is part of the concerted
united nations plan for the liberation
of europe
we're going to be liberated with last
autumn
[Music]
general eisenhower continued saying
we will accept nothing less than total
victory
in stormy weather conditions us airport
groups captured their first key town
british glider troops seized key bridges
east of kong
fire with the most intense bombardment
in naval history
in all the normandy invasion has
deployed 150 000 ground troops 15 000
tanks 5 300 ships
12 000 aircraft operation overlord the
largest amphibious assault in history
marks the beginning of the liberation of
occupied europe from nazi germany
as i'm sure you know i wasn't able to
shop and nevertheless you're 15 today so
here is my contribution to your future
career as a writer
oh
and this is from us a broach i wore when
i was your age i'm sure it will look
lovely on you there
oh it's really pretty thank you with all
of my heart to both of you and to peter
i feel so elegant and it's all thanks to
you
and this gift is from your mother
and your father of course
the art history book you wanted so much
and some necessary undergarments
they're nice
they're wonderful presents and i love
you very much and i want my sister thank
you everyone to have this no no you're
crazy marco no i i can't accept it it's
your very favorite necklace i can't take
it oh
but you're my favorite sister
i love you very much anne and i love you
too
dear kitty everyone is convinced that
the liberation is coming soon
will this long-awaited freedom which
still seems too wonderful too much like
a fairy tale ever come true
the best part of it is that i feel that
friends are approaching
[Music]
is it because i haven't poked my nose
outdoors for so long that i've grown so
crazy about everything to do with nature
watching the flowers bloom seeing the
birds the clouds the moon and the stars
all give me peace
and keep my hopes alive
i simply can't build up my hopes on a
foundation of confusion misery and death
because i still believe that deep down
people are good i can feel the
sufferings of millions and yet if i look
up into the heavens i think that it will
all come out right that this cruelty too
will end and that peace will return to
the world once again
well my friends as soon as we're
liberated i promise to take all of you
to the very best restaurant in amsterdam
and i will never touch another bean as
long as i live
and now let me tell you what i promise i
promise to keep smoking you out
but with the best cigars in the world ah
peter what are you going to oh uh
me
i'm gonna go and see all the fantastic
films i couldn't see being here and of
course ann will tell you which films you
have to see
[Laughter]
so wonderful to laugh and to dream
i'm going to pay a visit to every good
pastry shop in this city and i'm going
to buy you a whole new wardrobe and a
new fur coat
and you marco what will you do
i can think about is a nice hot bath and
staying in the tub for hours
excellent ideas
well
for one entire week i want to be all
alone
fine as long as you don't forget me
during that time i understand you
perfectly mrs franklin all right dear
i'll stay out of your way
and what about you anne
there are lots of things i can't wait to
do
like going back to school in september
walking freely around amsterdam and
especially seeing my friends again well
you mean you don't want to go to the
cinema
[Music]
dear kitty things are going well there's
more and more reason to hope really
everything is fine incredible news a
general in the german army tried to kill
hitler
what a pity that dare fear her managed
to escape with just a few cuts and burns
[Music]
well what good news do we have today it
seems
that the allies are gaining ground but
slowly
[Music]
oh that smells good does it
the recipe is simple you take some
canned food some potatoes red beans red
beans and more red beans
[Laughter]
[Music]
oh
[Applause]
[Music]
um
yes may i help you over chauffeur
zilbaba where is your director mr
coppoise
we know you are hiding jews here where
are they
aren't you ashamed to be helping jewish
trash
meep should have been here ages ago yes
you're right it's not likely to be so
late
what is it
[Laughter]
you're so silly
now these 50 jews hiding
they must be up there
oh yeah they are
don't move
there are eight of you just as the
person who betrayed you told us
search them they may be armed and then
search the whole place
i want you all out in the street in five
minutes do you understand bring me all
your valuables first
[Music]
goodbye kitty i won't forget you promise
you won't forget me
i don't want you to disappear
[Music]
i'm sure meep will protect you if she
can
little too
[Music]
get inside
quickly quickly
[Music]
hmm
so
[Music]
my dear dear kitty you're my friend and
i know you understand my message of
freedom and compassion for all the men
women and children of the world
regardless of their race religion or
belief
may you live in peace and help to make
this a better world for all humanity
[Music]
me
hmm
[Music]
ah
yes
oh it's a dream come true a diary friday
june 12th 1942 you were the nicest
present of all and i'm going to call you
kitty ever since the german invasion in
1940 amsterdam has been occupied by the
army and now we jews must wear a yellow
star in our clothing if not we can be
arrested beginning tomorrow we're going
to have to hide but daddy where are we
going i think it's better that i don't
tell you
here we are so this is the mysterious
hiding place welcome to our home in
hiding thank you so much for taking us
in dear kitty i can't tell you how
oppressive it is never to be able to go
outdoors
be careful not to be seen by anyone
outside i just want to breathe some
fresh air we have to whisper and tread
lightly during the day otherwise the
people in the warehouse which is just
below might hear us
also i'm very afraid we'll be discovered
and shot that is not exactly a pleasant
prospect
terrifying things are happening outside
jewish families are arrested day and
night and deported the whole world is at
war
i have fewer and fewer ration tickets
and things are more and more expensive
what's important is to keep your spirits
up and never lose heart my greatest wish
is to become a journalist i really
admire you you know what you want and
you're not a coward
i'm so happy to be here together with
you so mayan after the war what i want
to do is to publish a book that i'm
going to call the secret annex my diary
will certainly be a big help
[Music]
diary you are the nicest present of all
and i'm going to call you kitty
beginning tomorrow we're going to have
to hide
dear kitty i can't tell you how
oppressive it is never to be able to go
outdoors also i'm very afraid we'll be
discovered and shot
terrifying things are happening outside
the whole world
my greatest wish is to become a
journalist after the war what i want to
do is to publish a book that i'm going
to call the secret annex my diary will
certainly be a big help
[Music]